So I would like to start by telling you about one of my greatest friends,
بداية أود أن أحكي لكم عن أحد أقرب أصدقائي،
Okoloma Maduewesi.
أوكولوما مادويسي.
Okoloma lived on my street
كان أوكولوما يعيش بحينا
and looked after me like a big brother.
ويرعاني كأخ كبير.
If I liked a boy, I would ask Okoloma's opinion.
فكنت إن أعجبت بشاب، آخذ رأي أوكولوما.
Okoloma died in the notorious Sosoliso plane crash
توفي أوكولوما بتحطم طائرة سوسوليسو المريع
in Nigeria in December of 2005.
في نيجيريا ديسمبر 2005.
Almost exactly seven years ago.
منذ حوالي سبع سنوات مضت.
Okoloma was a person I could argue with, laugh with and truly talk to.
كان أوكولوما شخصا يمكنني أن أجادله وأضحك معه وأتحدث معه بصراحة تامة،
He was also the first person to call me a feminist.
كما أنه أول من سماني بالنسائية.
I was about fourteen, we were at his house, arguing.
كان عمري حوالي 14 سنة وكنا نتناقش في منزله.
Both of us bristling with half bit knowledge
كلانا مسلح بمعرفة جزئية
from books that we had read.
تراكمت من مطالعتنا للكتب.
I don't remember what this particular argument was about,
لا أتذكر بالضبط ما كان موضوع نقاشنا،
but I remember that as I argued and argued,
لكني أتذكر أني بينما كنت أحاكيه،
Okoloma looked at me and said, "You know, you're a feminist."
كان أوكولوما ينظر إلي وقال: "أتعلمين، أنت نسائية."
It was not a compliment.
ولم يكن ذلك مديحاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I could tell from his tone,
لقد خمنت ذلك من نبرة صوته،
the same tone that you would use to say something like,
تلك النبرة التي ستستخدمونها لقول شيء من قبيل:
"You're a supporter of terrorism."
"أنت تدعم الإرهاب."
(Laughter)
(صحك)
I did not know exactly what this word "feminist" meant,
لم أعلم وقتها معنى مصطلح "نسائية"،
and I did not want Okoloma to know that I did not know.
ولم أرغب في أن يعلم أوكولوما بأني لا أعرف معناها.
So I brushed it aside, and I continued to argue.
لذا وضعتها جانبا واستمريت في النقاش.
And the first thing I planned to do when I got home
فكان أول ما قررت فعله فور عودتي إلى المنزل
was to look up the word "feminist" in the dictionary.
هو البحث عن مصطلح "نسائية" بالقاموس.
Now fast forward to some years later,
دعونا نقفز بضع سنوات إلى الأمام،
I wrote a novel about a man who among other things beats his wife
كتبت رواية عن رجل يضرب زوجته
and whose story doesn't end very well.
لكن قصته لا تنتهي بشكل سعيد.
While I was promoting the novel in Nigeria,
وبينما كنت أسوق للرواية في نيجيريا،
a journalist, a nice, well-meaning man,
أخبرني صحفي، رجل حسن النية
told me he wanted to advise me.
أنه يريد نصحي.
And for the Nigerians here,
وبالنسبة للنيجيريين هنا،
I'm sure we're all familiar
أنا متأكدة بأنهم معتادون
with how quick our people are to give unsolicited advice.
على سرعة شعبنا في تقديم النصح دون طلب ذلك.
He told me that people were saying that my novel was feminist
أخبرني أن الناس يصفون روايتي بالنسائية
and his advice to me --
وكانت نصيحته لي...
and he was shaking his head sadly as he spoke --
وكان يهز رأسه حزنًا وهو يتحدث...
was that I should never call myself a feminist
أنه لا ينبغي أن أصف نفسي بالنسائية
because feminists are women who are unhappy
لأن الناشطات النسائيات هن نساء غير سعيدات
because they cannot find husbands.
لأنه لا يمكنهن العثور على أزواج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I decided to call myself "a happy feminist."
لذا قررت أن أدعو نفسي "النسائية السعيدة."
Then an academic, a Nigerian woman told me
ثم أخبرتني امرأة أكاديمية نيجيرية
that feminism was not our culture
أن الحركة النسائية ليست من ثقافتنا
and that feminism wasn't African,
وليست جزءًا من الثقافة الأفريقية،
and that I was calling myself a feminist
وأني أدعو نفسي بالنسائية
because I had been corrupted by "Western books."
لأني متأثرة "بالكتب الغربية."
Which amused me,
وهذا أمر أضحكني،
because a lot of my early readings were decidedly unfeminist.
لأن أغلب مطالعاتي الأولى لم تكن قطعا نسائية الصبغة.
I think I must have read every single Mills &amp; Boon romance published
أعتقد أني قرأت كل روايات دار النشر ميلز أند بوون
before I was sixteen.
قبل بلوغي سن السادسة عشرة.
And each time I tried to read those books
وفي كل مرة حاولت قراءة تلك الكتب
called "the feminist classics,"
المسماة " الكلاسيكية النسائية."
I'd get bored, and I really struggled to finish them.
كنت أصاب بالملل وعانيت الأمرين لأكمل قراءتها.
But anyway, since feminism was un-African,
وعلى أي حال، منذ أن دخلت الحركة النسائية على أفريقيا،
I decided that I would now call myself "a happy African feminist."
قررت أن أدعو نفسي "النسائية الأفريقية السعيدة."
At some point I was a happy African feminist who does not hate men
عند نقطة ما كنت تلك النسائية الأفريقية السعيدة غير الكارهة للرجال
and who likes lip gloss
والمحبة لملمع الشفاه
and who wears high heels for herself but not for men.
والتي ترتدي الكعب العالي لنفسها وليس للرجال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course a lot of this was tongue-in-cheek,
وبالطبع الكثير من تلك كانت مضحكة،
but that word feminist is so heavy with baggage, negative baggage.
لكن كلمة نسائية ثقيلة بحمولتها السلبية.
You hate men, you hate bras,
أنت تكرهين الرجال وحمالات الصدر
you hate African culture, that sort of thing.
والثقافة الأفريقية وأشياء من هذا القبيل.
Now here's a story from my childhood.
دعوني الآن أخبركم بقصة من طفولتي.
When I was in primary school,
عندما كنت تلميذة في الابتدائي،
my teacher said at the beginning of term that she would give the class a test
قالت معلمتي في بداية الفصل الدراسي أنها ستختبرنا
and whoever got the highest score would be the class monitor.
وسيكون صاحب أعلى درجة المسؤول عن القسم.
Now, class monitor was a big deal.
أن تكون المسؤول عن القسم هو أمر عظيم.
If you were a class monitor,
فإن كنت المسؤول عن القسم،
you got to write down the names of noisemakers --
يمكنك كتابة أسماء الأطفال المزعجين...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
which was having enough power of its own.
وكان ذلك في حد ذاته سلطة كبيرة.
But my teacher would also give you a cane to hold in your hand
بالإضافة إلى أن المعلمة ستمنحك عصا
while you walk around and patrol the class for noisemakers.
تتباهى بها خلال دوريتك في القسم بحثا عن المزعجين.
Now, of course you were not actually allowed to use the cane.
وبالطبع لا يسمح لك استعمال العصا.
But it was an exciting prospect for the nine-year-old me.
لكن الأمر كان فكرة مثيرة بالنسبة لطفلة في التاسعة من عمرها.
I very much wanted to be the class monitor.
أردت بشدة أن أصبح المسؤولة عن القسم.
And I got the highest score on the test.
وحصلت على أعلى درجة في الاختبار.
Then, to my surprise, my teacher said that the monitor had to be a boy.
بعدها، تفاجأت بمعلمتي تقول بأن على مسؤول القسم أن يكون صبيا.
She had forgotten to make that clear earlier
لقد نسيت أن توضح هذه النقطة في البداية
because she assumed it was ... obvious.
لأنها افترضت أن الأمر كان ... بديهيًّا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A boy had the second highest score on the test,
فأصبح الصبي صاحب ثاني أعلى درجة في الاختبار
and he would be monitor.
هو المسؤول في القسم.
Now, what was even more interesting about this
لكن الشيء الأكثر إثارة حول هذا الأمر
is that the boy was a sweet, gentle soul
هو أن ذاك الصبي كان لطيفًا ومسالمًا
who had no interest in patrolling the class with the cane,
غير مهتم بالقيام بدوريات في القسم حاملًا عصا بيده،
while I was full of ambition to do so.
بينما كنت أتوق إلى القيام بذلك الأمر.
But I was female and he was male,
لكني كنت أنثى وكان ذكرًا،
and so he became the class monitor.
وبالتالي أصبح هو المسؤول عن القسم.
And I've never forgotten that incident.
وعليه لم أنسى أبدًا تلك الحادثة.
I often make the mistake of thinking
وكثيرًا ما اعتقدت بالخطأ
that something that is obvious to me is just as obvious to everyone else.
أن ما هو بديهي بالنسبة لي هو كذلك للجميع.
Now, take my dear friend Louis
صديقي العزيز لويس
for example.
مثلًا.
Louis is a brilliant, progressive man,
كان لويس رجلا ذكيًّا وتقدميًّا و متحررًا،
and we would have conversations and he would tell me,
كنا نتحدث وكان يقول لي:
"I don't know what you mean by things being different or harder for women.
"لا أعلم ما تعنين بأن الأمور مختلفة وأصعب بالنسبة للنساء.
Maybe in the past, but not now."
ذلك ممكن في الماضي لكن ليس اليوم."
And I didn't understand how Louis could not see what seems so self-evident.
ولا أعلم كيف لم يتمكن لويس من رؤية الواقع.
Then one evening, in Lagos, Louis and I went out with friends.
وفي ليلة في لاغوس خرجت أنا ولويس مع بعض الأصدقاء.
And for people here who are not familiar with Lagos,
بالنسبة للحضور الذين لا يعرفون لاغوس،
there's that wonderful Lagos' fixture,
هناك تلك الخدمة الرائعة في لاغوس،
the sprinkling of energetic men who hang around outside establishments
مجموعة من الرجال النشطين المتواجدين حول المنشآت
and very dramatically "help" you park your car.
والذين "سيساعدوكم" بشكل استعراضي على ركن سيارتكم.
I was impressed with the particular theatrics
لقد اندهشت من الاستعراض المسرحي
of the man who found us a parking spot that evening.
للرجل الذي عثر لنا على مكان للركن تلك الليلة.
And so as we were leaving, I decided to leave him a tip.
وعندما كنا ذاهبين قررت أن أقدم له إكرامية.
I opened my bag,
فتحت حقيبتي،
put my hand inside my bag,
أدخلت يدي في حقيبتي،
brought out my money that I had earned from doing my work,
أخرجت المال الذي كسبته لقيامي بعملي،
and I gave it to the man.
وقدمته للرجل.
And he, this man who was very grateful and very happy,
وارتسمت على محيا ذلك الرجل قسمات الامتنان والسعادة،
took the money from me,
أخذ المال من يدي.
looked across at Louis
ونظر إلى لويس
and said, "Thank you, sir!"
وقال: "شكرًا لك، سيدي!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Louis looked at me, surprised,
نظر لويس إلي باندهاش،
and asked, "Why is he thanking me? I didn't give him the money."
وسأل: "لماذا يشكرني؟ لم أقدم له المال."
Then I saw realization dawn on Louis' face.
ثم رأيت وجه لويس بعد الاستيعاب.
The man believed that whatever money I had
اعتقد الرجل بأن المال الذي بحوزتي
had ultimately come from Louis.
مصدره من لويس.
Because Louis is a man.
فقط لكون لويس رجل.
Men and women are different.
الرجال والنساء مختلفون.
We have different hormones, we have different sexual organs,
لدينا هرمونات وأعضاء تناسلية مختلفة،
we have different biological abilities.
ولدينا قدرات بيولوجية مختلفة.
Women can have babies, men can't.
النساء ينجبن والرجال لا.
At least not yet.
على الأقل ليس الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Men have testosterone and are in general physically stronger than women.
الرجال لديهم التيستوستيرون وفي العموم هم أقوى جسديا من النساء.
There's slightly more women than men in the world,
النساء أكثر بقليل من الرجال في العالم،
about 52 percent of the world's population is female.
حوالي 52% من سكان العالم هن إناث.
But most of the positions of power and prestige are occupied by men.
لكن معظم المناصب القيادية والرفيعة يشغلها الرجال.
The late Kenyan Nobel Peace laureate,
الفقيدة الكينية الحائزة على نوبل للسلام،
Wangari Maathai,
وانجاري ماثاي،
put it simply and well when she said:
عرضت الأمر ببساطة وبشكل جيد عندما قالت:
"The higher you go, the fewer women there are."
"كلما ارتقيت في المجتمع، كلما قل تواجد النساء."
In the recent US elections we kept hearing of the Lilly Ledbetter law,
سمعنا كثيرًا عن قانون لليلي ليدبيتر خلال الانتخابات الأمريكية الأخيرة،
and if we go beyond the nicely alliterative name of that law,
وإذا تجاوزنا العنوان المنمق بشكل جميل لذلك القانون،
it was really about a man and a woman
فإن الأمر كان يتعلق بالفعل بالرجل والمرأة
doing the same job, being equally qualified,
اللذان يقومان بنفس العمل، ويملكان نفس المؤهل،
and the man being paid more because he's a man.
ولكن الرجل يتقاضى أجرًا أعلى لكونه رجلا.
So in the literal way, men rule the world,
وبشكل حرفي، الرجال يسيّرون العالم،
and this made sense a thousand years ago
وكان هذا الأمر منطقيًّا منذ آلاف السنين
because human beings lived then in a world
لأن الإنسان كان يعيش في عالم
in which physical strength was the most important attribute for survival.
كانت القوة الجسدية من أهم القدرات للبقاء على قيد الحياة.
The physically stronger person was more likely to lead,
الشخص الأقوى جسديًّا كان الأكفأ للقيادة،
and men, in general, are physically stronger.
والرجال، بشكل عام، هم أقوى جسديًّا.
Of course there are many exceptions.
وبالطبع هناك العديد من الاستثناءات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But today we live in a vastly different world.
لكننا اليوم نحيا في عالم جد مختلف.
The person more likely to lead is not the physically stronger person;
فالشخص الأكفأ للقيادة ليس بالقوي جسديًّا،
it is the more creative person, the more intelligent person,
بل الأكثر ابتكارًا وذكاءً
the more innovative person,
وإبداعًا
and there are no hormones for those attributes.
وليست هناك هرمونات خاصة بتلك القدرات.
A man is as likely as a woman to be intelligent,
فالرجل والمرأة متساويان على الأرجح في الذكاء
to be creative, to be innovative.
والابتكار والإبداع.
We have evolved;
لقد تطورنا؛
but it seems to me that our ideas of gender had not evolved.
لكن يبدو لي أن أفكارنا حول نوع الجنس لم تلتحق بالركب.
Some weeks ago, I walked into a lobby of one of the best Nigerian hotels.
منذ بضعة أسابيع، دخلت إلى أحد أفخم الفنادق النيجيرية.
I thought about naming the hotel, but I thought I probably shouldn't.
فكرت في ذكر اسم الفندق، لكن ارتأيت أنه لا ينبغي علي فعل ذلك.
And a guard at the entrance stopped me and asked me annoying questions,
استوقفني حارس عند المدخل وسألني بضعة أسئلة مزعجة،
because their automatic assumption is
لأنه في افتراضهم التلقائي
that a Nigerian female walking into a hotel alone is a sex worker.
أن امرأة نيجيرية تدخل إلى فندق بمفردها يعني أنها بائعة هوى.
And by the way,
وبالمناسبة،
rather than the demand for sex workers?
بدلًا من الطلب على العاملين في الجنس؟
In Lagos I cannot go alone into many "reputable" bars and clubs.
بلاغوس لا يمكنني الدخول منفردة للعديد من الحانات والملاهي الليلية "المعروفة".
They just don't let you in if you're a woman alone,
فهم لن يسمحون لكي بالدخول إن كنت بمفردك،
you have to be accompanied by a man.
يجب عليك أن تكوني بصحبة رجل.
Each time I walk into a Nigerian restaurant with a man,
في كل مرة دخلت إلى مطعم نيجيري صحبة رجل،
the waiter greets the man and ignores me.
يلقي النادل التحية على الرجل ويتجاهلني.
The waiters are products --
الندل هم نتاج...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At this some women felt like, "Yes! I thought that!"
بعض النساء قلن حيال ذلك: "نعم! أعتقد ذلك!"
The waiters are products of a society
الندل هم نتاج المجتمع
that has taught them that men are more important than women.
الذي يعلمهم أن الرجال أهم من النساء.
And I know that waiters don't intend any harm.
وأنا أعلم بأن الندل لا يقصدون أي إهانة بذلك.
But it's one thing to know intellectually and quite another to feel it emotionally.
لكن الدراية الفكرية تختلف عن الإحساس النفسي.
Each time they ignore me, I feel invisible.
في كل مرة تجاهلوني فيها، أشعر بأني غير مرئية
I feel upset.
وبالضيق،
I want to tell them that I am just as human as the man,
أرغب في أن أقول لهم بأني والرجل سيان في الإنسانية،
that I'm just as worthy of acknowledgment.
وأني أستحق نفس الاعتراف.
These are little things,
قد تكون تلك أمور صغيرة،
but sometimes it's the little things that sting the most.
لكن أحيانًا تكون الأمور الصغيرة أكثر إيلامًا.
And not long ago, I wrote an article
من فترة وجيزة، كتبت مقالًا
about what it means to be young and female in Lagos,
عن معنى أن تكوني شابة وأنثى في لاغوس،
and the printers told me,
وقد أخبروني في المطبعة،
"It was so angry."
أنه "كان مقالًا غاضبًا."
Of course it was angry!
بالطبع هو كذلك!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I am angry.
أنا غاضبة.
Gender as it functions today is a grave injustice.
نوع الجنس وفق الطريقة المعمول بها اليوم هو عبارة عن إجحاف.
We should all be angry.
علينا جميعًا أن نكون غاضبين.
Anger has a long history of bringing about positive change;
فللغضب تاريخ طويل في التغيير الإيجابي؛
but, in addition to being angry, I'm also hopeful.
لكني بالإضافة إلى كوني غاضبة، فأنا أيضًا كلي أمل.
Because I believe deeply in the ability of human beings
لأني أؤمن بقدرة البشرية
to make and remake themselves for the better.
على تطوير وإعادة تطوير نفسها نحو الأفضل.
Gender matters everywhere in the world,
فقضايا التمييز الجنسي مطروحة في العالم أجمع،
but I want to focus on Nigeria
لكني أريد التركيز على نيجيريا
and on Africa in general,
وأفريقيا بشكل عام،
because it is where I know, and because it is where my heart is.
لأنه مكان أعرفه ولأنه موطن قلبي.
And I would like today to ask
وأود اليوم أن أنادي
that we begin to dream about and plan for a different world,
لكي نبدأ في الحلم والتخطيط لعالم مختلف،
a fairer world,
لعالم أكثر إنصافًا،
a world of happier men and happier women who are truer to themselves.
لعالم من رجال ونساء سعداء وصادقين مع أنفسهم.
And this is how to start:
وهذه هي طريقة البدء:
we must raise our daughters differently.
علينا تربية بناتنا بشكل مختلف.
We must also raise our sons differently.
علينا تربية أبنائنا بشكل مختلف.
We do a great disservice to boys on how we raise them;
طريقة تربيتنا للفتيان تضرهم بشكل كبير؛
we stifle the humanity of boys.
نحن نخنق البشرية في الفتيان.
We define masculinity in a very narrow way,
نعرف الرجولة بشكل ضيق،
masculinity becomes this hard, small cage
بحيث تصبح الرجولة كقضبان قاصية لقفص صغير
and we put boys inside the cage.
لنسجن فيه الفتيان.
We teach boys to be afraid of fear.
نعلم الأولاد الخوف من الخوف.
We teach boys to be afraid of weakness, of vulnerability.
ونعلمهم الخوف من الضعف والتأثر.
We teach them to mask their true selves,
نعلمهم إخفاء وجههم الحقيقي،
because they have to be, in Nigerian speak, "hard man!"
لأنه عليهم أن يكونوا، وفق المعتقد النيجيري، "رجل حازم!"
In secondary school, a boy and a girl, both of them teenagers,
في الثانوية، ولد وبنت كلاهما مراهقين،
both of them with the same amount of pocket money, would go out
وبنفس مبلغ مصروف الجيب، سيخرجان معًا
and then the boy would be expected always to pay,
سينتظر دائمًا من الولد دفع الحساب،
to prove his masculinity.
ليثبت رجولته.
And yet we wonder why boys are more likely to steal money from their parents.
ومع ذلك نتساءل لماذا من المرجح أكثر أن يسرق الفتيان المال من آبائهم.
What if both boys and girls were raised
ماذا لو ربي الفتيان والفتيات
not to link masculinity with money?
على عدم ربط الرجولة بالمال؟
What if the attitude was not "the boy has to pay"
ماذا لو كان السلوك ليس "الولد عليه الدفع"
but rather "whoever has more should pay?"
بل "كل من بحوزته المال يدفع؟"
Now, of course because of that historical advantage,
وبالطبع، بناء على هذا الامتياز التاريخي،
it is mostly men who will have more today,
فإن الرجال، في الغالب، هم من سيتقاضى أكثر اليوم،
but if we start raising children differently,
لكن إذا قمنا بتربية أبنائنا بشكل مختلف،
then in fifty years, in a hundred years,
فإنه خلال خمسون أو مائة سنة،
boys will no longer have the pressure of having to prove this masculinity.
لن يبقى هناك ضغط على الفتيان يحتم عليهم إثبات رجولتهم.
But by far the worst thing we do to males,
إلا أن أسوأ ما نفعله بالذكور،
by making them feel that they have to be hard,
بجعلهم يشعرون بأنه عليهم أن يكونوا حازمين،
is that we leave them with very fragile egos.
هو أننا نربي فيهم شعورًا جد هش بذواتهم.
The more "hard man" the man feels compelled to be,
فكلما شعر الرجل أن عليه أن يكون "حازمًا"،
the weaker his ego is.
كلما كان شعوره بذاته أضعف.
And then we do a much greater disservice to girls
وبالتالي نتسبب في ضرر أكبر للفتيات
because we raise them to cater to the fragile egos of men.
لأننا نربيهن على إرضاء ذاك الشعور الهش بالذات لدى الرجال.
We teach girls to shrink themselves, to make themselves smaller,
نربي الفتيات على تقليص ذواتهن وتقزيمها،
we say to girls,
نقول للفتيات،
"You can have ambition, but not too much."
"يمكن أن يكون لديكن طموح، ولكن ليس كثيرًا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"You should aim to be successful, but not too successful,
"عليكن أن تهدفن إلى النجاح، ولكن ليس نجاحًا كبيرًا،
otherwise you would threaten the man."
لأنه في تلك الحالة ستهددن نجاح الرجل."
If you are the breadwinner in your relationship with a man,
إن كنتِ معيل الأسرة في علاقتك مع الرجل،
you have to pretend that you're not,
فعليك التظاهر بالعكس،
especially in public,
وخاصة في العلانية،
otherwise you will emasculate him.
وإلا ستنزعين عنه صفة الرجولة.
But what if we question the premise itself?
لكن ماذا لو وضعنا الفرضية نفسها موضع تساؤل؟
Why should a woman's success be a threat to a man?
لماذا قد يهدد نجاح المرأة الرجل؟
What if we decide to simply dispose of that word,
ماذا لو قررنا بكل بساطة التخلص من تلك الكلمة،
and I don't think there's an English word I dislike more than "emasculation."
وأعتقد أني لا أبغض تعبيرا في الإنجليزية أكثر من "أخذت رجولته."
A Nigerian acquaintance once asked me
سألتني إحدى معارفي النيجيرية
if I was worried that men would be intimidated by me.
عما إذا كنت أخشى من أن يَهَابَنِي الرجال.
I was not worried at all.
لم أكن أخشى ذلك على الإطلاق.
In fact, it had not occurred to me to be worried
في الواقع، لم أكن أرغب في أن يهابني أحد
because a man who would be intimidated by me
لأن الرجل الذي سيهابني
is exactly the kind of man I would have no interest in.
هو عينه الرجل الذي لن أهتم به.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But still I was really struck by this.
لكن هذا ما يدهشني حقاً.
Because I'm female, I'm expected to aspire to marriage;
لأني أنثى ومن المفترض أن أصبو إلى الزواج؛
I'm expected to make my life choices
علي وأنا أقوم باختياراتي في الحياة
always keeping in mind that marriage is the most important.
أن أستحضر دائما بأن الزواج هو أهم شيء.
A marriage can be a good thing;
الزواج يمكن أن يكون أفضل شيء؛
it can be a source of joy and love and mutual support.
يمكنه أن يكون مصدر سعادة وحب وتكامل.
But why do we teach girls to aspire to marriage
لكن لماذا علينا تربية الفتيات على التطلع إلى الزواج
and we don't teach boys the same?
ولا نعلم الفتيان نفس الشيء؟
I know a woman who decided to sell her house
أعرف امرأة قررت بيع بيتها
because she didn't want to intimidate a man who might marry her.
لأنها لم تشأ أن تخيف الرجل الذي قد يتزوجها.
I know an unmarried woman in Nigeria who, when she goes to conferences,
أعرف امرأة غير متزوجة في نيجيريا كانت عندما تذهب إلى الندوات
wears a wedding ring
ترتدي خاتم زواج
because according to her,
لأنه وفقًا لكلامها،
she wants the other participants in the conference to "give her respect."
كانت ترغب أن "يحترمها" باقي المشاركين في الندوة.
I know young women who are under so much pressure
أعرف شابة تتعرض لضغط رهيب
from family, from friends, even from work to get married,
من أسرتها وأصدقائها وحتى في عملها لتتزوج،
and they're pushed to make terrible choices.
وهن مجبرات على القيام باختيارات فظيعة.
A woman at a certain age who is unmarried,
المرأة التي بلغت سنًّا معينًا دون زواج،
our society teaches her to see it as a deep, personal failure.
يعلمها مجتمعنا أن ترى الأمر كفشل شخصي ذريع.
And a man at a certain age who is unmarried,
والرجل الذي بلغ سنًّا معينًا دون زواج،
we just think he hasn't come around to making his pick.
نفكر بأن النحلة لم تقرر بعض اختيار الزهرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's easy for us to say,
من السهل علينا قول:
"Oh, but women can just say no to all of this."
"لكن يمكن للنساء أن يقلن لا لكل ذلك."
But the reality is more difficult and more complex.
لكن الواقع أصعب وأعقد بكثير.
We're all social beings.
نحن جميعا مخلوقات اجتماعية.
We internalize ideas from our socialization.
نحن نتشرب بأفكار ناتجة عن نشأتنا الاجتماعية.
Even the language we use
حتى طريقة كلامنا
in talking about marriage and relationships illustrates this.
في الحديث عن الزواج والعلاقات توضح ذلك.
The language of marriage is often the language of ownership
فكلامنا عن الزواج هو غالبا كلام بيع وشراء
rather than the language of partnership.
أكثر منه كلام عن شراكة.
We use the word "respect"
نستعمل كلمة "احترام"
to mean something a woman shows a man
لنقصد به شيء ما تظهره المرأة للرجل
but often not something a man shows a woman.
لكن ليس ما يظهره الرجل في الغالب للمرأة.
Both men and women in Nigeria will say --
سيقول الرجال والنساء في نيجيريا على حد سواء...
this is an expression I'm very amused by --
وهو تعبير يضحكني كثيرًا...
"I did it for peace in my marriage."
"أقوم بذلك للحفاظ على استقرار زواجي."
Now, when men say it,
الآن، تلك العبارة في فم الرجال،
it is usually about something that they should not be doing anyway.
هي في العادة حول أمر لا يفترض أن يقوموا به.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sometimes they say it to their friends,
أحيانا يقولون ذلك لأصدقائهم،
it's something to say to their friends in a kind of fondly exasperated way,
إنه أمر يقولونه لأصدقائهم بنبرة من الاستياء العميق،
you know, something that ultimately proves how masculine they are,
كأنه أكثر شيء يثبت مدى رجولتهم
how needed, how loved.
وأهميتهم والحب المكنون لهم.
"Oh, my wife said I can't go to the club every night,
"قالت زوجتي أنه لا يمكنني الذهاب إلى الملهى كل ليلة،
so for peace in my marriage, I do it only on weekends."
وحفاظا على استقرار زواجي أذهب فقط في نهاية الأسبوع."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, when a woman says, "I did it for peace in my marriage,"
لكن عندما تقول امرأة: "أفعل ذلك للحفاظ على استقرار زواجي."
she's usually talking about giving up a job,
فهي في العادة تتحدث عن التخلي عن عملها
a dream,
أو حلمها
a career.
أو مسارها المهني.
We teach females that in relationships,
نحن نعلم الأنثى على أنه في العلاقات،
compromise is what women do.
التنازل هو ما تقدمه المرأة.
We raise girls to see each other as competitors --
نربي الفتيات على النظر إلى بعضهن كمنافسات...
not for jobs or for accomplishments, which I think can be a good thing,
ليس من أجل الوظائف أو تحقيق الذات، والذي في نظري هو أمر جيد،
but for attention of men.
لكن في جلب انتباه الرجال.
We teach girls that they cannot be sexual beings
نعلم الفتيات على أنهن لسن مخلوقات جنسية
in the way that boys are.
كما هو الحال للفتيان.
If we have sons, we don't mind knowing about our sons' girlfriends.
إن كان لدينا أولاد ذكور، فإنه لا يهمنا معرفة صديقات أولادنا.
But our daughters' boyfriends? God forbid.
لكن أصدقاء بناتنا؟ لا سمح الله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But of course when the time is right,
لكن، وبالطبع، في الوقت المناسب،
we expect those girls to bring back the perfect man to be their husbands.
ننتظر من تلك الفتيات أن يحضرن الرجل المثالي ليصبح زوجهن.
We police girls, we praise girls for virginity,
نراقب الفتيات ونمدح عذريتهن،
but we don't praise boys for virginity,
لكن لا نفعل ذلك مع عذرية الفتيان،
and it's always made me wonder how exactly this is supposed to work out because ...
وهذا ما شغل بالي دائما كيف يعمل ذلك بالضبط لأن...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I mean, the loss of virginity is usually a process that involves ...
أقصد، فقدان العذرية هي عملية تتطلب في العادة...
Recently a young woman was gang raped in a university in Nigeria,
مؤخرا، تعرضت فتاة لاعتصاب جماعي في جامعة بنيجيريا،
I think some of us know about that.
أظن أن بعضنا قد سمع بذلك.
And the response of many young Nigerians, both male and female,
وكان رد العديد من الشباب النيجيريين ذكور وإناث على حد سواء،
was something along the lines of this:
بشكل ما على هذا المنوال:
"Yes, rape is wrong.
"نعم، الاغتصاب أمر خاطئ.
But what is a girl doing in a room with four boys?"
لكن ماذا كانت تفعل الفتاة في غرفة مع أربعة فتيان؟"
Now, if we can forget the horrible inhumanity of that response,
إذا تناسينا هذا الجواب البشع غير الإنساني،
these Nigerians have been raised to think of women as inherently guilty,
فإن أولئك النيجيريين تربوا على فكرة أن النساء مذنبات بطبيعتهن،
and they have been raised to expect so little of men
وربوا لينتظروا القليل من الرجال
that the idea of men as savage beings without any control
بحيث أن فكرة الرجال ككائنات متوحشة وخارجة عن السيطرة
is somehow acceptable.
هي بشكل ما مقبولة.
We teach girls shame.
نعلم الفتيات العيب.
"Close your legs." "Cover yourself."
"ضمي قدميك." "غطي نفسك."
We make them feel as though by being born female
نحن نجعلهن يعتقدن منذ ولادتهن
they're already guilty of something.
بأنهن مذنبات بشيء ما.
And so, girls grow up to be women
وعليه، تنمو الفتيات ليصبحن نساء
who cannot see they have desire.
غير قادرات على تقبل أن لديهن رغبات.
They grow up to be women who silence themselves.
يكبرن ليصبحن نساء يقمعن أنفسهن عن الكلام.
who cannot say what they truly think,
يكبرن ليصبحن نساء غير قادرات على الإفصاح عن رأيهن،
and they grow up --
ويكبرن...
and this is the worst thing we did to girls --
وهذا أسوأ ما نفعله بالفتيات...
they grow up to be women who have turned pretense into an art form.
يكبرن ليصبحن نساء فنانات في التظاهر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I know a woman who hates domestic work,
أعرف امرأة تكره الأعمال المنزلية،
she just hates it,
إنها تكرهها وحسب،
but she pretends that she likes it,
لكنها تتظاهر بأنها تحبها،
because she's been taught that to be "good wife material"
لأنها تعلمت أنه لتكون "زوجة جيدة"
she has to be -- to use that Nigerian word --
عليها أن... لاستعمال تلك الكلمة النيجيرية...
very "homely."
"سيدة بيت."
And then she got married,
وقد تزوجت بعدها،
and after a while her husband's family began to complain that she had changed.
وبعد مدة بدأت أسرة زوجها تتذمر من أنها قد تغيرت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, she had not changed,
في الواقع، هي لم تتغير،
she just got tired of pretending.
بل تعبت من التظاهر فقط.
The problem with gender,
الإشكال مع الجنس،
is that it prescribes how we should be
أنه يحدد الحال الذي يجب أن نكون عليه
rather than recognizing how we are.
بدلًا من الاعتراف بالحال الذي نحن عليه.
Now imagine how much happier we would be,
تخيلوا كم كنا سنكون أكثر سعادة
how much freer to be our true individual selves,
وأحرارًا في أن نكون على طبيعتنا الحقيقية،
if we didn't have the weight of gender expectations.
لو لم يكن علينا تحمل ثقل الانتظارات المرتبطة بجنسنا.
Boys and girls are undeniably different biologically,
لا يمكن إنكار اختلاف الفتيان والفتيات بيولوجيًّا،
but socialization exaggerates the differences
لكن التنشئة الاجتماعية تبالغ في الاختلافات
and then it becomes a self-fulfilling process.
ومن ثم تصبح العملية تلقائية التطبيق في الواقع.
Now, take cooking for example.
الطبخ مثلًا.
Today women in general are more likely to do the housework than men,
حاليًا المعتقد السائد هو أن النساء تقمن بأعمال البيت أكثر من الرجال،
the cooking and cleaning.
الطبخ والتنظيف.
But why is that?
لكن لم ذلك؟
Is it because women are born with a cooking gene?
هل لأن النساء ولدن بجينات الطبخ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or because over years they have been socialized to see cooking as their role?
أو لأنهن على مر السنوات أنشئن اجتماعيا على النظر إلى الطبخ كمهمة مرتبطة بهن؟
Actually, I was going to say that maybe women are born with a cooking gene,
الحقيقة، كنت سأقول، ربما أن النساء يولدن بجينات الطبخ،
until I remember that the majority of the famous cooks in the world,
إلى أن تذكرت بأن غالبية الطهاة المشهورين عالميًّا،
whom we give the fancy title of "chefs,"
والذين نناديهم بلقب "شيف"،
are men.
هم رجال.
I used to look up to my grandmother
اعتدت على النظر إلى جدتي
who was a brilliant, brilliant woman,
التي كانت امرأة ذكية، جد ذكية،
and wonder how she would have been
وأتساءل كيف كان سيكون حالها
if she had the same opportunities as men when she was growing up.
لو أتيحت لها نفس فرص الرجال عندما كانت صغيرة.
Now today, there are many more opportunities for women
اليوم، هناك العديد من الفرص المتاحة للنساء
than there were during my grandmother's time
مقارنة بوقت جدتي
because of changes in policy, changes in law,
بفضل التغيير في السياسات والقوانين،
all of which are very important.
وهذا أمر مهم للغاية.
But what matters even more is our attitude, our mindset,
لكن ما يهم أكثر هي مواقفنا وطريقة تفكيرنا،
what we believe and what we value about gender.
ما نؤمن به ونقدره فيما يتعلق بالجنس.
What if in raising children
ماذا لو نربي أطفالنا
we focus on ability instead of gender?
مركزين على قدراتهم بدلًا من نوع الجنس؟
we focus on interest instead of gender?
ماذا لو نركز في تربية أطفالنا على قدراتهم بدلًا من نوع الجنس؟
I know a family who have a son and a daughter,
أعرف أسرة لديها طفل وطفلة،
both of whom are brilliant at school,
كلاهما نجيبان في المدرسة،
who are wonderful, lovely children.
وهما طفلان رائعان ولطيفان.
When the boy is hungry, the parents say to the girl,
عندما يكون الطفل جائعًا، يقول الأبوين للطفلة:
"Go and cook Indomie noodles for your brother."
"اذهبي واطبخي معكرونة الإندومي لأخيك".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, the daughter doesn't particularly like to cook Indomie noodles,
الابنة لا تحب طهو معكرونة الإندومي على الخصوص،
but she's a girl, and so she has to.
لكنها فتاة وبالتالي عليها القيام بذلك.
Now, what if the parents,
الآن، ماذا لو علَّم الأبوين،
from the beginning,
منذ البداية،
taught both the boy and the girl to cook Indomie?
الفتى والفتاة معا طبخ الإندومي؟
Cooking, by the way, is a very useful skill for boys to have.
بالمناسبة، يعتبر الطبخ مهارة مفيدة للفتيان.
I've never thought it made sense to leave such a crucial thing,
لم أفهم أبدا المغزى من ترك تعلم تلك المهارة الحيوية،
the ability to nourish oneself --
وهي القدرة على إطعام الشخص نفسه...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
in the hands of others.
بين يدي أشخاص آخرين.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I know a woman who has the same degree and the same job as her husband.
أعرف امرأة لديها نفس درجة زوجها العلمية ونفس الوظيفة.
When they get back from work, she does most of the housework,
وعند عودتهما من العمل، فإنها تقوم بمعظم أعمال البيت،
which I think is true for many marriages.
هو الأمر في اعتقادي بمعظم الزيجات.
But what struck me about them
لكن ما أدهشني حولهما
was that whenever her husband changed the baby's diaper,
أنه كلما غيَّر زوجها الحفاظة للطفل،
she said "thank you" to him.
تقول له: "شكرًا".
Now, what if she saw this as perfectly normal and natural
ماذا لو نظرت إلى الأمر على أنه عادي وطبيعي
that he should, in fact, care for his child?
أن عليه، في الواقع، الاعتناء بطفله؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm trying to unlearn many of the lessons of gender
أحاول التخلص من العديد من الدروس التي تعلمتها
that I internalized when I was growing up.
حول نوع الجنس عندما كنت صغيرة.
But I sometimes still feel very vulnerable in the face of gender expectations.
لكن أحيانا أشعر باني ضعيفة أمام الانتظارات المرتبطة بنوع الجنس.
The first time I taught a writing class in graduate school,
عندما درست لأول مرة فصل الكتابة في الكلية،
I was worried.
كنت قلقة.
I wasn't worried about the material I would teach
لم أكن قلقة من المادة التي سألقيها
because I was well-prepared,
لأني كنت مستعدة جيدًا،
and I was going to teach what I enjoy teaching.
وكنت سأدرِّس ما أحب تدريسه.
Instead, I was worried about what to wear.
بدلًا من ذلك، كنت قلقة بشأن ما سأرتديه.
I wanted to be taken seriously.
كنت أريد أن أحمل على محمل الجد.
I knew that because I was female
كنت أعرف أنه لكوني أنثى
I will automatically have to prove my worth.
سيكون علي تلقائيا إثبات جدارتي.
And I was worried that if I looked too feminine,
وكنت قلقة بأنه إن بالغت في إظهار أنوثتي،
I would not be taken seriously.
لن أحمل على محمل الجد.
I really wanted to wear my shiny lip gloss and my girly skirt,
كنت أرغب حقا في وضع ملمع الشفاه وارتداء تنورتي الأنثوية خاصتي،
but I decided not to.
لكن قررت ألا أفعل.
Instead, I wore a very serious,
بدلًا من ذلك، ارتديت بذلة جد رسمية،
very manly and very ugly suit.
جد رجالية وقبيحة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because the sad truth is that when it comes to appearance
لأن الحقيقة المحزنة هي أنه عندما يتعلق الأمر بالمظهر
we start off with men as the standard, as the norm.
نتخذ الرجال كمعيار وكقاعدة.
If a man is getting ready for a business meeting,
إذا كان رجل يستعد لاجتماع عمل،
he doesn't worry about looking too masculine
فهو لا يهتم إن بدى أكثر رجولة
and therefore not being taken for granted.
وبالتالي أن لا يحمل على محمل الجد.
If a woman has to get ready for business meeting,
وإذا أردات امرأة أن تستعد لاجتماع عمل،
she has to worry about looking too feminine
سيكون عليها القلق من أن تبدو أكثر أنوثة من اللازم
and what it says and whether or not she will be taken seriously.
وما عليها قوله وإن كانت ستؤخذ على محمل الجد أو لا.
I wish I had not worn that ugly suit that day.
وددت لو لم أرتدي يومها تلك البذلة القبيحة.
I've actually banished it from my closet, by the way.
بالمناسبة، لقد نفيتها من خزانتي.
Had I then the confidence that I have now to be myself,
لو كنت أملك وقتها نفس الثقة بالذات التي لدي اليوم،
my students would have benefited even more from my teaching,
كان ليستفيد طلابي من تدريسي بشكل أكبر،
because I would have been more comfortable
لأني كنت سأكون أكثر ارتياحًا
and more fully and more truly myself.
وعلى سجيتي بشكل أكبر.
I have chosen to no longer be apologetic for my femaleness
وقد اخترت ألا أستمر في الاعتذار عن كوني أنثى
and for my femininity.
وأنوثتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I want to be respected in all of my femaleness
وأنا أريد أن أُحترم بكامل أنوثتي
because I deserve to be.
لأني أستحق ذلك.
Gender is not an easy conversation to have.
نوع الجنس ليس موضوع نقاش بسيط.
For both men and women,
سواء للرجال أو النساء،
to bring up gender is sometimes to encounter almost immediate resistance.
الحديث عن نوع الجنس يجابه أحيانا بمقاومة فورية.
I can imagine some people here are actually thinking,
يمكنني تخيل بعض الحضور هنا يقولون لأنفسهم:
"Women too do sef."
"النساء كعادتهن."
Some of the men here might be thinking,
وقد يقول بعض الرجال هنا لأنفسهم:
"OK, all of this is interesting,
"هذا أمر مثير للاهتمام،
but I don't think like that."
لكني لا أفكر بهذا الشكل."
And that is part of the problem.
وهذا جزء من المشكل.
That many men do not actively think about gender
لأن العديد من الرجال لا يفكرون بجدية في نوع الجنس
or notice gender
أو يلاحظونه
is part of the problem of gender.
هو جزء من مشكل نوع الجنس
That many men, say, like my friend Louis,
أن العديد من الرجال يعتقدون كصديقي لويس،
that everything is fine now.
بأن كل شيء على ما يرام الآن.
And that many men do nothing to change it.
وأن العديد من الرجال لا يقومون بأي شيء لتغيير ذلك.
If you are a man and you walk into a restaurant with a woman
إن كنت رجلا وذهبت إلى المطعم مع امرأة
and the waiter greets only you,
وألقى النادل التحية عليك وحدك،
does it occur to you to ask the waiter,
هل يتبادر إلى ذهنك أن تسأله:
"Why haven't you greeted her?"
"لماذا لم تلقي التحية عليها؟"
Because gender can be --
لأن الجنسانية يمكن أن تكون...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, we may repose part of a longer version of this talk.
في الواقع، هناك نسخة مطولة من هذه المحادثة.
So, because gender can be a very uncomfortable conversation to have,
بما أن الجنسانية يمكن أن تكون نقاشًا غير مريح،
there are very easy ways to close it, to close the conversation.
هناك طرق جد سهلة لإقفاله، إقفال النقاش فقط،
So some people will bring up evolutionary biology and apes,
البعض مثلًا سيأتي بحجة علم الأحياء التطوري والقردة،
how, you know, female apes bow down to male apes
والذي كما تعرفون تخضع فيه أنثى القرد للذكر
and that sort of thing.
وغيرهما من هذه الأمور.
But the point is we're not apes.
لكن الأمر هو أننا لسنا قردة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Apes also live on trees and have earthworms for breakfast,
فالقردة تعيش فوق الأشجار وتأكل الديدان على الفطور،
and we don't.
أما نحن فلا.
Some people will say, "Well, poor men also have a hard time."
بعض الناس سيقولون: "حسنا، الرجال المساكين هم أيضا يعانون."
And this is true.
وهذا صحيح.
But that is not what this --
ولكن هذا ليس...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is not what this conversation is about.
لكن هذا ليس موضوع هذه المحادثة.
Gender and class are different forms of oppression.
الجنسانية والطبقية هما نوعان مختلفان من الظلم.
I actually learned quite a bit about systems of oppression
في الواقع لقد تعلمت الكثير حول أنظمة الظلم
and how they can be blind to one another
وكيف يمكن لإحداها ألا يرى الآخر
by talking to black men.
بالحديث إلى الرجال السود.
I was once talking to a black man about gender
كنت أتحدث ذات مرة مع رجل أسود حول الجنسانية
and he said to me,
فقال لي:
"Why do you have to say 'my experience as a woman'?
"لم عليك القول (من خلال تجربتي كامرأة)؟
Why can't it be
لما لا تقولين
'your experience as a human being'?"
(من خلال تجربتي كإنسانة)؟"
Now, this was the same man
كان ذلك نفس الرجل
who would often talk about his experience as a black man.
الذي غالبًا ما يتحدث عن تجربته كرجل أسود.
Gender matters.
الجنسانية أمر مهم.
Men and women experience the world differently.
الرجال والنساء يختبرون العالم بشكل مختلف.
Gender colors the way we experience the world.
نوع الجنس يؤثر على طريقة اختبارنا للعالم.
But we can change that.
لكن يمكننا تغيير ذلك.
Some people will say,
سيقول بعض الناس:
"Oh, but women have the real power,
"لكن النساء تملكن القوة الحقيقية،
bottom power."
القوة من الخلف."
And for non-Nigerians, bottom power is an expression
ولغير النيجيريين، عبارة القوة من الخلف
which I suppose means something like a woman
والتي أعتقد أنها تعني شيئا ما من قبيل
who uses her sexuality to get favors from men.
المرأة التي تستعمل أنوثتها للحصول على ما تريد من الرجال.
But bottom power is not power at all.
لكن تلك القوة ليست كذلك على الإطلاق.
Bottom power means that a woman
تلك القوة تعني امرأة
simply has a good root to tap into, from time to time --
تملك قاعدة جيدة تعتمد عليها من حين لآخر...
somebody else's power.
لتحصل على القليل من قوة الآخر.
And then, of course, we have to wonder
وبالطبع، علينا التساؤل بعدها
what happens when that somebody else is in a bad mood,
عما يحدث عندما يكون ذاك الآخر في مزاج سيئ
or sick
أو مريضًا
or impotent.
أو خانته القوة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Some people will say that a woman being subordinate to a man is our culture.
البعض سيقول أن خضوع المرأة للرجل جزء من ثقافتنا.
But culture is constantly changing.
لكن الثقافة في تغير دائم.
I have beautiful twin nieces who are fifteen and live in Lagos.
لدي ابنتا أخت وهما توأمان عمرهما 15 سنة تعيشان في لاغوس.
If they had been born a hundred years ago
لو قدر لهما أن تولدا منذ مئات السنين
they would have been taken away and killed.
لأخذتا على جنب وقتلتا.
Because it was our culture, it was our culture to kill twins.
لأنها كانت ثقافتنا، التي كانت تقضي بقتل التوأم.
So what is the point of culture?
إذا ما دور الثقافة؟
I mean there's the decorative,
أقصد هناك الزينة،
the dancing ...
الرقص ...
but also, culture really is about preservation and continuity of a people.
لكن الثقافة الحقيقية تتعلق بالمحافظة على مجموعة من الناس واستمراريتهم.
In my family,
في أسرتي،
I am the child who is most interested in the story of who we are,
أنا الابنة الأكثر اهتمامًا بمن نكون،
in our traditions,
وبتقاليدنا،
in the knowledge about ancestral lands.
وبالتعرف على أراضي أجدادنا.
My brothers are not as interested as I am.
إخوتي الذكور ليسوا مهتمين بذلك مثلي.
But I cannot participate,
لكن لا يمكنني المشاركة.
I cannot go to umunna meetings,
لا يمكنني الذهاب إلى اجتماعات الأومونا.
I cannot have a say.
ليس لي الحق في الكلام.
Because I'm female.
لأني أنثى.
Culture does not make people,
ليست الثقافة من يحدد هوية الناس،
people make culture.
الناس هم من يحددون هوية الثقافة.
So if it is in fact true --
إذا كان حقا...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So if it is in fact true
إذا كان حقًّا
that the full humanity of women is not our culture,
أن إنسانية النساء بالكامل ليست ثقافتنا،
then we must make it our culture.
إذا علينا أن نجعلها كذلك.
I think very often of my dear friend, Okoloma Maduewesi.
أفكر كثيرًا بصديقي العزيز أوكولوما مادويسي
May he and all the others who passed away in that Sosoliso crash
أرجو له ولكل الآخرين الذين قضوا في تحطم طائرة سوسوليسو
continue to rest in peace.
السلام الأبدي.
He will always be remembered by those of us who loved him.
سيبقى حيا في ذاكرة كل من أحبوه.
And he was right that day many years ago when he called me a feminist.
وكان محقا يومها عندما وصفني بالنسائية منذ عدة سنوات.
I am a feminist.
أنا نسائية.
And when I looked up the word in the dictionary that day,
وعندما بحثت يومها عن المصطلح في المعجم،
this is what it said:
كان تعريفها كالتالي:
"Feminist: a person who believes in the social, political
"نسائية: شخص يؤمن بالمساواة الاجتماعية والسياسية
and economic equality of the sexes."
والاقتصادية بين الجنسين."
My great grandmother, from the stories I've heard,
ومن خلال القصص التي سمعتها عن جدة أمي،
was a feminist.
فإنها كانت نسائية.
She ran away from the house of the man she did not want to marry
لأنها هربت من بيت الرجل الذي لم ترغب في الزواج به
and ended up marrying the man of her choice.
وانتهى بها المطاف لتتزوج الرجل الذي اختارته.
She refused, she protested, she spoke up
لقد رفضت واعترضت ونادت بأعلى صوتها
whenever she felt she was being deprived of access, of land, that sort of thing.
عندما أحست أنها حرمت حق الحصول على أرض لها وأشياء من هذا القبيل.
My great grandmother did not know that word "feminist,"
لم تكن جدة أمي تعرف كلمة "نسائية"
but it doesn't mean that she wasn't one.
لكن هذا لا يعني أنها لم تكن كذلك.
More of us should reclaim that word.
على المزيد منا استرجاع تلك الكلمة.
My own definition of feminist is:
أنا أعرف كلمة نسائية كالتالي:
"A feminist is a man or a woman
"نسائية هي كل رجل أو امرأة
who says --
تقول...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A feminist is a man or a woman who says,
نسائية هو كل رجل أو امرأة تقول:
"Yes, there's a problem with gender as it is today,
"نعم، هناك مشكل في الجنسانية بوضعها الراهن،
and we must fix it.
وعلينا تصحيح الوضع.
We must do better."
علينا القيام بأمر أفضل."
The best feminist I know
أفضل نسائية أعرفها
is my brother Kene.
هو أخي كيني.
He's also a kind, good-looking, lovely man,
كما أنه رجل لطيف ووسيم ومحب،
and he's very masculine.
وغاية في الرجولة.
Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)